<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The way to wealth wherein is plainly taught a most present remedy for sedicion. Wrytten and imprinted by Robert Crowley the .vii. of Februarye in the yere of our Lorde. a thousand fiue hu[n]derd [et] fiftie. In Elie rentes in Holburne cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum.</title>
            <author>Crowley, Robert, 1518?-1588.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1550</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19673</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6096</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105142</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840872</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840872</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5414</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19673)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5414)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 34:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The way to wealth wherein is plainly taught a most present remedy for sedicion. Wrytten and imprinted by Robert Crowley the .vii. of Februarye in the yere of our Lorde. a thousand fiue hu[n]derd [et] fiftie. In Elie rentes in Holburne cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum.</title>
                  <author>Crowley, Robert, 1518?-1588.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S. Mierdman for Robert Crowley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1550]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The period after "fiftie" on the title page is actually three dots within round brackets.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Social conditions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5414:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5414:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ The way to wealth, wherein is plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly taught a moſt preſent remedy for Sedicion. Wrytten and imprinted by Robert Crowley the .vii. Of Februarye in the yere of our LORDE. A thouſand fiue hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derd &amp; fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</p>
            <p>☞ In Elie rentes in Holburne</p>
            <p>¶ Cum priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</p>
            <q>
               <l>☞ Who ſo thou be that doeſt deſyre,</l>
               <l>to liue and good dayes ſe.</l>
               <l>Loke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in thy tonge and thy lyps,</l>
               <l>none yl or diſceite be.</l>
               <l>Fle from yl and do that good is,</l>
               <l>whereof commeth no blame.</l>
               <l>Seke thou for peace diligently,</l>
               <l>and then enſue the ſame.</l>
               <bibl>Pſalm. xxxiiii.</bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:5414:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5414:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ By what meanes Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicion maye be put awaye, and what diſtruction wil folow if it be not put away ſpedely. Conſultatio Robert Crolei</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maye playne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceiue the greate hurte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> (of late daies) Sedicion hath done in thys realme, &amp; that all wyſe men maye eſilye gather, what greater hurte is lyke to enſue, if it be not ſpedely ſene vnto: it ſhalbe euery true Englyſhmans duty forth wyth to employe his whole ſtudy to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouynge ſo greate an euel oute of ſo noble a realme and commone wealth, leſte haply (if throughe negligence it growe and take deper rote) it be ſhortly to ſtronge and more ſuerly grounded, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that it maye be rooted oute, wythoute the vtter deſtruction of the whole realme. For what can be more true, then that whych the trueth it ſelfe hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken? Euery kyngdome (ſayeth Chriſte) that
<pb facs="tcp:5414:3"/> is deuided in it ſelfe,<note place="margin">Mathew. xii.</note> ſhall be broughte to nought. Intendynge therefore to playe the parte of a true Englyſhman, and to do all that in me ſhall ly to plucke thys ſtincking wede vp by the rote: I ſhal in thys good bu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſines do as in their euell exerciſe the diſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playars (that gladlye woulde, but haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge to playe for) do. Holde the candle to them that haue wherewyth, and wyll ſette luſtily to it. And ſo doyng, I ſhal be no leſſe worthy the name of a true herted Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man then the trumpettar is, worthy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of a man of war, thoughe he do not in dede fyght, but animate and encourage other.</p>
            <p>Sedition therfore beinge a daungerous diſeaſe in the bodie of a commen wealth: muſte be cured as the expert Phiſicians do vſe to cure the daungerous diſeaſes in a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall bodie. And as the moſte ſubſtanciall waye in curinge diſeaſes, is by puttinge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye the cauſes wherof they grewe: ſo is it in the pullinge vp of Sedition. For if the cauſe be once taken awaye, then muſte the effecte nedes faile. If the rote be cut of: the braunch muſt nedes die. The boughes can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not budde, if the tree, haue no ſappe.</p>
            <p>Geue eare therfore (o my countrey men) geue eare. And do not diſdaine to heare the aduiſe of one of the leaſte of poure brethren
<pb facs="tcp:5414:3"/> for the matter requireth euerie mans coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell,<note place="margin">Daniel. xiii.</note> and God reueiled vnto younge Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, that whiche the whole counſell of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon perceiued not. Geue eare, I ſaye, and if I tell you trueth, be not aſhamed to do y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I bid, thoughe ye knowe me to be at youre commaundement.<note place="margin">Gene. xxi</note> For Abraham was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to do at the biddinge of Saraie his wife, becauſe he knewe that hir biddinge was gods will. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Niniuites did at the biddinge of pore Ionas,<note place="margin">Ionas. iii.</note> ſit in ſackecloth &amp; aſhes, becauſe they perceiued that he tolde them the trueth. Yea cruell Herode did not refuſe to heare Iohn Baptiſte, becauſe the thinge whiche he told him was true.<note place="margin">marcke vi.</note> Leaſte you therfore ſhulde be more loftie then the Babilonians, more ſhamefaſt then Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, more ſtubborne then the Niniuites, &amp; more cruell then Herod, geue eare and patientlye heare what I ſhal ſaye.</p>
            <p>The cauſes of Sedition muſte be roted oute. If I ſhuld demaunde of the pore man of the contrey what thinge he thinketh to be the cauſe of Sedition: I know his anſwere<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He woulde tel me that the great fermares, the graſiers, the riche but hares, the men of lawe, the marchauntes, the gentlemen, the knightes, the lordes, and I can not tel who, Men that haue no name becauſe they are
<pb facs="tcp:5414:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:5414:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:5414:5"/> doares in al thinges that ani gaine hangeth vpon. Men without conſcience. Men vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly voide of goddes feare. Yea men that liue as thoughe there were no God at all. Men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> would haue all in their owne handes, men that would leaue nothyng for others, men that would be alone on the earth, men that be neuer ſatiſfied, Cormerauntees, gredye gulles, yea men that would eate vp menne women &amp; chyldren: are the cauſes of Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. They take our houſes ouer our head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, they bye our growndes out of our han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, they reyſe our rentes, they leauie great (yea vnreaſonable) fines, they encloſe oure commens. No cuſtome, no lawe or ſtatute can kepe them from oppreſſyng vs, in ſuch ſorte, that we knowe not whyche waye to turne vs to lyue. Very nede therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayneth vs to ſtand vp agaynſt them. In the countrey we can not tarye, but we muſt be theyr ſlaues and laboure tyll our hertes braſt, and then they muſt haue al. And to go to the cities we haue no hope, for there we heare that theſe vnſaciable beaſtes haue all in theyr handes. Some haue purchaſed and ſome taken by leaſes, whole allyes, whole rentes, whole rowes, yea whole ſtreats and lanes, ſo that the rentes be reyſed, ſome dou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, ſome triple, and ſome four fould to that
<pb facs="tcp:5414:5"/> they were wythin theſe .xii. yeres laſt paſt. Yea ther is not ſo much as a garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grownd fre from them. No remedye therfore, we muſt nedes fight it out, or elſe be brought to the lyke ſlauery that the french men are in. Theſe Idle bealies wil deuour al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhal get by our ſore labour in our youth, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhal be old and impotent, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal we be driuen to begge and craue of them that wyl not geue vs ſo muche as the crowmes tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fall from their tables: Such is the pytie w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſe in them. Better it were therfore, for vs to dye lyke men, then after ſo great miſery in youth to dye more miſerably in age.</p>
            <p>Alaſſe poore man, it pitieth me to ſe the myſerable eſtate that thou arte in. Both for that thou arte ſo oppreſſed of them by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſhouldeſt be defended from oppreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and alſo for that thou knoweſt not thy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye in thys great miſery. Thou art not ſo much oppreſſed on the one ſide, but thou art more deſtituted on the other ſyde. They y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhould noriſh and defend thy body in thy la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour do oppreſſe the: &amp; they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhuld fede thy ſoule &amp; ſtrengthen thy mind to beare al this pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, do leaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> alone. If thy ſhepherde had bene a diligent watchman, &amp; had eſpied the woulfe comyng vpon the, before y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> hadſt bene w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in his reach he wold, haue ſtepped be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twene
<pb facs="tcp:5414:6"/> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> &amp; thine enemi, &amp; enſtructed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in ſuch ſort y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> though he had come in nine ſhepe ſkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, yet he ſhoulde not haue deceiued thy ſyghte. The deuell ſhoulde neuer haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded the y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou myghteſt reuenge thyne owne wronge. The falſe prophetes ſhoulde neuer haue cauſed the to beleue that thou ſhouldeſte preuaile againſte them with the ſwerde, vnder whoſe gouernaunce God hath apointed the to be. He would haue told the that to reuenge wronges, is in a ſubiect to take and vſurpe the office of a kinge and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently the office of God. For the king is goddes miniſter to reuenge the wronges done vnto the innocent. As he that taketh in hande therefore, or preſumeth to do anye of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice vnder a kinge, not beinge lawfully cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto it, preſumeth to do the office of a kinge: ſo he that taketh in hand to do the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a king, taketh goddes office in hand. We reade that oure ſauioure Chriſt beinge in the eſtimation of the worlde but a priuate man,<note place="margin">Luke .x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> wold not walke out of the boundes of that vocacion. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a certaine ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> came vnto him &amp; deſired that he would co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund hys brother to deuide the enheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wyth him: he axed who had appointed him to be iudge in ſuche matters. And againe when the woman take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in adultery was broughte vnto hym: he ſhoulde not geue ſentence
<pb facs="tcp:5414:6"/> of the lawe againſte her, but axed hir if any man had comdemned hir, and vpon hir de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall let hir go. If theſe examples,<note place="margin">Iohn. viii.</note> with the terrible ſtories of Corah, Datha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Abira and Abſolom had ben diligently beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into thine heade:<note place="margin">Numeri. xvi</note> thou wouldeſte (no doubte) haue qui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eted thy ſelfe,<note place="margin">ii. Reg. xviii</note> and haue ſuffered thy ſelfe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to haue bene ſpoyled of al together yea and thy bodie toren in peces rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou wouldeſt haue taken on the more then thou art called vnto. For no cauſe can be ſo great to make it lawful for the to do againſte god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des ordinaunce: But thy ſhepeherde hathe bene negligent as (alas the while) all ſhepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herdes be at this daie, and hath not enſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the aright. He eſpied not the wolf before he had woried the, or happlye he knewe him not frome a ſhepe. But it is moſte like he was but an hirelinge, and cared for no more but to be fedde with the milcke &amp; fatlinges and cladde with the woule, as the greateſte numbre of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that beare the name of ſhepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herde in Englande be at this daie. Yea per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunce he had many flockes to kepe &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore was abſent from them al, leauing with euerye flocke a dogge that woulde rather worye a ſhepe then driue away the woulfe, wel, brother, theſe be greate plages, &amp; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth the ſynnes to be greate that haue
<pb facs="tcp:5414:7"/> deſerued theſe ſo great and intollerable pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges at goddes hande. Returne to thi conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence therfore, and ſe if thou haue not deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued all this and more to. Conſider firſte if thou haue loued thy neighboure as thy ſelf, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider if thou haue done nothing vnto him that thou wouldeſte not that he ſhoulde do vnto the. Loke if thou haue not gone about, to preuent him in any bargen that thou haſt ſene him about, loke if thou haue not crafte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vndermined him to get ſome thing out of his hand, or to deceiue him in ſome bargein. Loke if thou haue not laboured him oute of his houſe or ground. Se if thou haue not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed him falſely or of malice, or elſe geuen falſe euidence againſte him: Se if thou haue not geuen euell counſell to his wife or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes which might turne him to diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Conſider if thou haue not deſired and wiſhed in thine herte to haue his commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, if thou mighteſt without blame of the worlde haue broughte it aboute. For God loketh vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the herte and if thine herte haue bene infected with ani of theſe euilles then haſte thou bene abominable in the ſight of God, and haſte deſerued theſe plages at goddes ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. Now if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> befou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d abhominable in thy be hauoure towardes thy neighboure what ſhalt thou be founde troweſt thou in
<pb facs="tcp:5414:7"/> thy demaners to god ward? God requireth thine whole hert, thyne whole mynd, and al the powers of thy body and ſoule. Thou ſhalt loue thy Lord God wyth all thy lyfe, wyth al thy mynd, and wyth al thy ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth. That is to ſay,<note place="margin">Math. xxii.</note> ther ſhalbe nothynge in the whych thou ſhalt not apply wholly to the loue of thy Lord God. But how was it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for the to loue God (whom thou ſeeſt not) ſyth thou loueſt not thy Brother whom thou ſeeſt? God requireth the to loue him e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. And how often haſt thou gone whole dayes togither, whole weakes, yea whole yeres, and neuer thought once to loue hym aryght? How many and how great benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes haſt thou receyued at goddes hand, and howe vnthanckful haſt thou bene for them, thynckynge that thou haſte gotten them by thyne owne laboure and not receyued them frely at goddes hand? As though God had not geuen the thy lyfe, thyne health, and thy ſtrength to laboure. Yea and as thoughe it were not God only that geueth the increaſe of euerye mans labour. But knowynge by thyne owne creacion and bryngyng vp, and alſo by the yonge fruite that God ſendeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> of thy bodi, &amp; further by the frutes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth and cauſeth yerely to growe out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is a god almyghty; yet y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt
<pb facs="tcp:5414:8"/> not honoured him as God,<note place="margin">romaynes .l.</note> but haſt turned the glorie of God into an Image made af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſhape or ſimilitude of mortall man, renuinge and ridinge from place to place to ſeke and to honoure thinges of thine owne makeinge, crienge and callinge vpon them in thy nede and paying vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy vowes and thancking the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for thyne health receiued doinge them dayly worſhipe and reuerence in the temples, and beſtowinge thine almes vpon them in deckinge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſetting ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes before them. Biſide this thou haſte put confidence of ſaluacion in pardones that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſte bought, in prayers that thou haſt hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or mumbled vp thy ſelfe, in maſſes that thou haſt cauſed to be ſaide, and in worckes that thou thy ſelfe haſte fantaſied, and haſte not thanckefullye receyued the free mercye of God offered vnto the in Chriſt in whom onlye thou maiſte haue remiſſion of thy ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: and therfore God hath geuen the vp in to a reprobate minde to do the thinge that is not beſeminge.<note place="margin">Rom. i.</note> Euen to ſtande vp againſte God and goddes ordinaunce, to refuſe his holy word, to delite in lies and falſe fables, to credite falſe prophetes and to take weape<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in hand againſt goddes choſen miniſters, I ſaye his choſen miniſters. For be they good or bad they are goddes choſen. If they be
<pb facs="tcp:5414:8"/> good: to defende the innocente<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> If they be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell: to plage the wicked. If thou wilt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that God ſhall deliuer the or thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren from the tirannie of them that oppreſſe the: lament thine olde ſinnes,<note place="margin">i. Eſdras .i.</note> and endeuour emendment of life. And then he that cauſed King Cirus to ſend the Iewes home to Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem againe: ſhall alſo ſtire vp our yong king Edward to reſtore the to thy liberty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and to geue ſtraight charge that non ſhalbe ſo bolde as once to vexe or trouble the.<note place="margin">Prouerb. xxi.</note> For the herte of a kinge is in goddes hand, &amp; as he turneth the riuers of water, ſo turneth he it. Beſure therfore, that if thou kepe thy ſelfe in obedience and ſuffer al this oppreſſion patiently, not geueing credite vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to falſe prophecies that tel the of victori but to the worde of God that telleth the thy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: thou ſhalt at the time, and after the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that God hath alredie pointed,<note place="margin">Ezech. xi.</note> be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered. Perchaunce God wyl take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thine oppreſſours their hard ſtony hertes &amp; geue them hertes of fleſhe, for it is in hys pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſo to do. Let him alone therfore. Reade the prophecie of Ieremie, and eſpecially the ſeuen and twentie Chapter,<note place="margin">Reade Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie hys pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phecie.</note> the eighte and twentie and the nine and twenti, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou ſhalte learne thy duetie in captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, and howe vayne a thynge it is to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite
<pb facs="tcp:5414:9"/> the prophetes that Prophecie vyc-torie to theym that haue by their ſynnes deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to be led awaye captyue, yea and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine captiue till ſuche time as the time be complete duringe whiche God hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to puniſhe them. And know thou for certentie, that if thou be ſtil ſtouberne, God wil not leaue the ſo. He will bringe the on thy knees, he wyl make the ſtoupe. If the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tlemen and rulars of thy countreie ſhoulde be to weake for the, he would bringe in ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge nations to ſubdue the (as the Babiloni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ans did the Iewes) and leade the away cap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiue. So that refuſing to ſerue in thine own countrie, thou ſhalte be made a ſlaue in a ſtrainge contrei. Quiet thy ſelfe therfore, &amp; ſtriue not againſte the ſtreame. For thi ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes haue deſerued this oppreſſion, and God hath ſent if the as a iuſt rewarde for thy ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: &amp; be y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> neuer ſo loth, yet nedes ſuſtaine it thou muſte. Apointe thy ſelfe therfore to beare it. Let it not be layed vpon the in vain let it do the thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God hath ſent it for, let it cauſe the to acknowledge thy ſinne, repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it and become altogether a new man. That in the day when God ſhall deliuer the, his name maie be glorified in the. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God ſhal ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plentie of true prophets, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal go before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in puriti of life, and godli doctrine.
<pb facs="tcp:5414:9"/> They ſhal not come or ſend .iiii. times in an yere and no more, neyther ſhal they ſet one togather vp the tenth of thyne encreaſe to their behoufe, and leaue the deſtitute of a di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligente guyde (as thy ſhepherdes do nowe a dayes) but God hath promiſed by hys prophete to take a waye theſe ſhepeherdes from the, and to commyt the to the kepynge of Dauid hys fayethful ſeruaunte, that is to ſaye to ſuch as wyll be as diligent in fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng the, as Dauid was in gouernyng the people of whom he had gouernau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Geue eare therfore ye ſhephardes of thys church of Englande. Ye Byſhoppes, ye Deanes, Archdiacons and Canons, ye Perſons and ye Vicares what ſoeuer ye be, that receyue any parte of the tenth of mens yerelye en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe or any other patrimony of preachers geue eare to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet Ezechiel, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Lord y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bad him ſpeake vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſheperdes of Iuda, byddeth hym ſpeake vnto you nowe alſo. Thou ſonne of manne ſayth the Lord: prophecye agaynſt the ſhepherdes of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, prophecy and ſay vnto thoſe ſhephear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dis: thus ſayeth the Lord God. Wo be to the ſhepherdes of England,<note place="margin">Ezech. xxxiiii.</note> that haue fed them ſelues. What ought not thoſe ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herdes to haue fed thoſe flockes of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. Ye eate the fatte, and decke youre ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues
<pb facs="tcp:5414:10"/> with the woule, &amp; the mutton that is fat, ye kil to fede vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but theſe ſilli ſhepe ye fede not. The ſoroweful &amp; penſiue ye haue not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forted, the ſicke ye haue not healed, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> broken ye haue not bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vp, the ſtray ſhepe ye haue not brought againe nor ſought for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſt. But w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> extreme crueltie ye haue plaied the lordes ouer them &amp;c. I nede not to reherſe more of this prophets ſaiyng vnto you, for ye know where to haue it and haue leyſure inough to ſeke it, for ought that I ſe you buſied withal onleſſe it be with purchaiſinge landes for youre heires &amp; finde fingered ladies, whoſe woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>like, behauiour and motherlike houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wifry ought to be a lighte to al wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that dwell aboute you, but is ſo fare otherwiſe that vnleſſe ye leaue them landes to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye them wythall, no man wyll ſet a pinne by them whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you be gone. Wel loke to this geare be tyme, leaſte perhappes it beede a ſcabbe emonge you. I woulde not your wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues ſhoulde be taken from you: but I wold you ſhoulde kepe them to the furtheraunce of goddes trueth wherof ye profeſſe to be teacheares. Let youre wiues therefore put of theire fine frockes and frenche hoodes &amp; furniſhe them ſelues with al pointes of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt houſewifery, and ſo let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be an helpe to youre ſtudie and not a lette. S. Paul tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth
<pb facs="tcp:5414:10"/> you not to make them ladies or gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen.<note place="margin">i. Timo. iii.</note> Neither doeth he teache you to be ſo gredie vpon liueings, that for the liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge ſake ye will take vpon you the dueties of twentie men and yet do not the duetie of one, no ſome of you be not able to do anye part of one dutie. If goddes worde do alow it that one of you ſhulde be a deane in one place, a canone in an other, a parſone here and a parſone there, a maiſter of an houſe in Oxforde or Cambridge and an officer in the kinges houſe, and yet to do none of the duities herof thorowly: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſet your pennes to the paper and ſatiſfie vs bi goddes word and we wil alſo helpe you to oure power to ſatiſfie the conſciences of them that be offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded at youre doinges herin. If you can not do ſo: then geue ouer youre pluralities and make your vnſaciable deſires geue place to goddes trueth. Content your ſelfe without competent liueinge, and faile not to be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente in doinge the duetie therof. But if ye wyll do neither of boeth: truſte to it ye ſhall heare more of it. Youre checkinge of one or two in a corner can not ſtop euerye ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes mouth in a matter of trueth beynge ſo great an infamie to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel of god which ye pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe. And if ye wil nedes hold ſtil your plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities for your lordlike liueing ſake doubt
<pb facs="tcp:5414:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> ye not ye wyll be charged with that whiche ye woulde ſeme to be cleare of. For a great numbre of youre vnworthye curates haue bene the ſtirrars vp of the ſimple people in the late tumultes that haue bene, where as if you had not robbed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that which thei paye yearely to haue a learned and Godly teachar, they had bene better enſtructed, as appeared by the quietnes that was emonge them that had ſuch ſhepeherdes. Well bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Thou I ſaie that art thus oppreſſed on the one ſide and deſtituted on the other: take mine aduiſe with the. Submit thy ſelf who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the wyll of God. Do thy laboure tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, cal vpon God continually. I meane not that thou ſhuldeſt be euer muttering on thy beads, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ſhouldeſt haue any beads, but my meaninge is, that thou ſhouldeſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue thine harte lifted vp vnto God, for ſo meaneth Sainte Paul when he ſayeth. I would men ſhould pray alwayes and in all places, liftinge vp theire pure handes. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And in all thy doinges let thy deſire be that Goddes wil be fulfilled in the, and what ſo euer God ſendeth the, holde the content w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and render vnto him moſt hertie tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ckes for that he dealeth ſo mercifully with the, acknowledginge that bi his iuſtice he might poure oute vpon the mo plages then euer
<pb facs="tcp:5414:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> were heard of. And when thou commeſte to thy pariſhe church, if thy curate be an euell liue ar,<note place="margin">Math. xxiii.</note> then remember what Chriſte ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to his diſciples. When the ſcribes and pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes do ſet them downe vpon Moſes ſeate, then do al that they commaunde you to do, but do not as they do, for they ſay &amp; do not. Remember this I ſaie, and what ſo euer thi curate biddeth the do whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſitteth on chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſeate, that is, when he readeth the bible vnto the: that do thou. But folowe not his examples. Do not as thou ſeeſt him do, but at thy firſte entraunce into the church, lifte vp thine herte vnto god, and deſire of hym that he wyll geue the his holye ſpirit to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and lighten the eies of thine herte that thou maiſt ſe and perceiue the true meaning of all the ſcriptures that thou ſhalte heare reade vnto the that dai. And ſo ſhalt thou be ſure, that thoughe thy curate were a deuell and would not that any man ſhoulde be the better for that whiche he readeth: yet thou ſhalt be edified and learne as much as ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be neceſſarye for thy ſaluacion. And for thy ſake god ſhall make thy curate (that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe wold mumble in the mouth &amp; drounde his wordes) to ſpeake out plainly, or elſe he ſhall geue the ſuch a gift that thou ſhalt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande him plainely.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ii.</note> Of ſuche power is
<pb facs="tcp:5414:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> God, for when the Apoſtles ſpake in the he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brue tonge onlye, al that were preſent heard euery man his own language. Doubt thou not therfore but if thou be deſirous to learne thy duetie out of that thy curate readeth to the: God wil make it plaine vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, though it be not plainlye reade. For he that coulde make the hebrue tonge (which ſowndeth far otherwiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other tonges do) ſownd al ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of languages, to euerie man his owne language: can alſo make thine owne langu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age ſownde plaine vnto the, though it were not ſpoken anye thinge plaine. Thus ſeeſte thou that the cauſe of Sedition is not where thou laieſt it, for I haue declared to the that thine owne ſinne is the cauſe that thou arte Sedicious. For Sedition is poured vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the to plage thy former ſinne withall. Becauſe thou kneweſt God bi his creatures and yet dideſt not honoure him as God, he hath ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the ouer into a reprobate ſence to do the thinge that is vnſemelye, euen to ſtande vp againſte God and goddes ordinaunce, as I haue ſayde before.</p>
            <p>Nowe if I ſhould demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the gredie cormerauntes what thei thinke ſhuld be the cauſe of Seditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: they would ſaie, the paiſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t knaues be to welthy, proue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der pritheth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. They knowe not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, they knowe no obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, they regard no lawes, thei would
<pb facs="tcp:5414:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> haue no gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thei wold haue al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> like the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, they would haue al thinges com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune. Thei would not haue vs maiſters of that which is our owne. They wil appoint vs what re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t we ſhal take for our groundes We muſt not make the beſte of oure owne. Theſe are ioly felowes. Thei wil caſte dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne our parches, &amp; laie our paſtures ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thei wil haue the law in their own ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. They wil play the kinges. They wyll compel the kinge to grafit theyr requeſtes. But as they like their fare at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breake faſte they had this laſte ſomer, ſo let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do againe. They haue ben metely well coled, and ſhalbe yet better coled if they quiet not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues. We wyll tech the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to know theyr betters. And becauſe they wold haue al co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mone, we wil leaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothing. And if they once ſtirre againe or do but once cluſter togither, we wil hang the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at their own dores. Shal we ſuffer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vila<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nes to diſproue our doynges? No, we wil be lordes of our own &amp; vſe it as we ſhal thinke good.</p>
            <p>Oh good maiſters, what ſhuld I cal you? you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue no name, you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue ſo many oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cupacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; trads y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther is no on name mete for you. You vnge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. You chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les chikens I ſay. Geue me leue to make an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwere for the pore Ideotes ouer whom ye triumphe in this ſorte. And this one thing I ſhal deſire of you that ye report me not to
<pb facs="tcp:5414:13"/> be one that fauoureth their euel doinges (for I take God to witnes I hate doeth theyre euell doinges and youres alſo) but geue me leaue to tel you as frely of your faultes, as I haue alreadi told them of theires. And for aſmuch as you be ſtronge and they weake, I ſhall deſire you to beare with me though I be more erneſt in rebuking your faultes, then I was in rebuking theirs.</p>
            <p>True it is, the pore men (who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye cal pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunte knaues) haue deſerued more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you can deuiſe to laie vpon them. And if euerye one of them were able and ſhoulde ſuſtaine as much puniſhment as thei al were able to ſuſtaine yet could thei not ſuſtaine the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei haue deſerued. But yet if their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence wer laied in an equall balaunce with yours (as no doubt thei are in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight God) do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t not but you ſhould ſone be aſhamed of yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re parte. For what can you laye vnto their charge, but they haue had examples of the ſame in you? If you charge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyth diſobedience: you were firſte diſobedient.</p>
            <p>For without a law to beare you, yea contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie to the law which forbiddeth al maner of oppreſſion &amp; extortio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; that more is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to conſcience, the ground of al good lawes, ye encloſed frome the pore theire due com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mones, leauied greater fines the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heretofore
<pb facs="tcp:5414:13"/> haue bene leauied, put them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the liberties (and in a maner enheritaunce) that they held vp cuſtome, &amp; reiſed theire rentes. Yea whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther was a law ratified to the contrary, you ceaſed not to finde meanes either to compel your tenantes to conſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to your deſire in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſinge, or elſe ye found ſuch maiſterſhip y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man durſte gaine ſaye your doinges for feare of diſpleaſure. And what obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wed you, when the kinges proclamations were ſent forthe, and commiſſions directed for the laying open of your encloſures, and yet you lefte not of to encloſe ſtil? Yea what obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was this which ye ſhewed at ſuch time as the kinges moſte honourable coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell perceiueinge the: grudginge that was emong the people, ſent forth the ſecond pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation concerning your negligence or rather contempte in not laieinge open that which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trari to the good eſtatutes made in parliament you had encloſed? It appeareth by your doinges that there was in you nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obedience to your prince and his laws, nor loue to your contrei. For if there had be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obedience in you: you wold forthwith haue put al his laws in executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the vttermoſt of youre power. And if you had loued your contrei, woulde you not haue preuented the great deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced bi the reaſone
<pb facs="tcp:5414:14"/> of your vnſaciable deſire: I am ſure you be not rulars in your contrey, but ye can ſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what is likely to folowe vpon ſuch op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, &amp; eſpeciallye in a realme that hath hertofore had a noble and a valiaunte enm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minalti. But graunt ye were ſo beaſtiſh: yet haue you not lacked the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that haue tolde you of it both by wordes and writtinges. You haue ben tolde of it I ſaye, and haue had the threatninges of God laied plainlye before your eies wherin you muſt nedes ſe the ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce of God hanging ouer your heades for your lacke of mercy. Ther is not one ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie of the Bible that ſerueth to declare how readi God is to take vengeaunce for the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of his people: but the ſame hath ben declared vnto you to the vttermoſte, beſide the notable hiſtories and cronicles of thys realme, wherin doeth moſt plainly appeare the iuſtice of god in the reuenging of his peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, at ſuch time as they haue kept the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in quiete obedience to their prince &amp; rulers &amp; their deſtruction when they haue rebelled.</p>
            <p>Wittinglye and willinglye therfore ye haue boeth diſobeied youre kinge and his lawes, and alſo broughte youre contrei into the miſeri it is in, bi pulling vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your ſelf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vengeaunce of god whiche of his iuſtice he can not holde backe from ſuch people as do
<pb facs="tcp:5414:14"/> wyllinglye and wittynglye oppreſſe him in his membres, in ſuch ſorte as ye haue done. Howe you haue obeyed the lawes in ruke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge together of fermes, purchaiſinge and prollynge for benefices, robbing the people of good miniſters therby, al the world ſeeth and all godly hertes lament. Loke the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes made in the time of our late ſouerayne of famouſe memorye Henrie the .viii. &amp; ſaye if ye maye by thoſe eſtatutes (taken in theyr true meaninge) either beinge no prieſtes nor ſtudentes in the vniuerſities haue benifices, or other ſpirituall promotions (as you call theym for ye are aſhamed to calle theym, miniſtracious becauſe ye neyther wyll nor can miniſter) or beinge prieſtes haue plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities of ſuch miniſtrations. Well I wyl burden you no more wyth youre faultes, leaſte perhappes you can not wel beare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> But thys I ſhall ſaye vnto you. You ſhall neuer the ſoner be gentlemen for your ſhout oppreſſion, nor the later haue thynges in pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uate for that ye let youre tenauntes lyue by you vpon theyre laboure. And thincke not to proſpere the better in youre vnſatiable deſyre for that you tryumphe ſo Lorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke ouer the poore Captyfes, that beynge ſeduced by the vayne hope of vyctorye promyſed theym in piuyſhe Prophecies
<pb facs="tcp:5414:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> haue greatly offended God by rebellion: for the greater their offence is, the greater ſhall your plage be when it commeth. For you haue bene the only cauſe of theyr offence. If he therfore that is the occaſion of one mans fallyng vnto any kynd of vyce, were better haue a mylſtone tied aboute hys necke and be caſt into the depe ſea wythall: what ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be thought of you that haue bene the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſo many mens fallyng into ſo deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſynne and treſpaſſe agaynſte God, as to diſtrube y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole eſtate of their contrei with the great perill and daunger of their anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Kyng in hys tender age, whoſe bloud (if he had periſhed) ſhould haue bene required at your handes as the bloud of al them that haue periſhed ſhal? Oh merciful god, were it not that goddes mercy is more then your ſynnes can be: ther were no way but to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peyre of forgeuenes. But god is not onely mightye in mercy &amp; able to forgeue al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the whole world: but he is alſo redye to forgeue al that returne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr wycked wayes, and w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a conſtant faith &amp; ſure beleue to obtayne do call on hym for mercye. I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſe you therfore, &amp; in the name of Chriſt (whoſe name you beare) I require you, that w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out delaye ye returne to your hertes &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge your greuous and manifold of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences,
<pb facs="tcp:5414:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted in your behauiour to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the poore members of Chriſt (youre bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren boeth by religion and nation) whome you haue ſo cruellye oppreſſed, wyſhe euen from the bottome of your hertes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you had neuer done it. Be fully determined to make reſtitucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that ye haue miſſe take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though ye ſhould leaue your ſelues nothynge. For better is a cleare conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hour of deth in a beggars boſome, then mountaynes of gould w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a conſcience y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is gilty, Wiſhe that you had contented your ſelues w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that ſtate wherin your fathers left you, and ſtriue not to ſet your children aboue the ſame, leſt god take vengaunce on you boeth ſodenly, when ye be moſt haſtie to clime. And if for youre worthines god haue called you to offyce ſo that ye may wyth good conſcience take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtate that ye he called vnto: then ſe you deale iuſtly in all poyntes, &amp; folowe not fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy lucre to make your children Lordes, but ſtudye to furniſh them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al knowledge and godly maners, that they may worthily ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede you. Grudge not to ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people growe in wealth vnder you, neither do you inuent waies to kepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bare: leſt haply it chaunce vnto you as it did to Kinge Nabuchodono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer and hys ſeruauntes when they diuiſed wayes to kepe the Hebrues in ſlauery ſtil,<note place="margin">Exodi. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5414:16"/>
            <p>They rebelled not but quietly did theyr la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, referrynge theyr cauſe to God. They prepared not for warres neither had any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fidence in theyr owne ſtrength, but when the Egiptians thought to haue had a faire day at them:<note place="margin">Exodi. xii.</note> God drowned them al in the redde ſea, and draue theyr deade bodies on land in ſuch ſorte that they whom they thoughte to kepe ſtyll in ſlauerye myght eaſyly take the ſpoyle of them. Thincke not therfore, but if the people quiete the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in theyr oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and cal vnto God for deliueraunce: he wyll by one meane or other geue them the ſpoile of their oppreſſours. He is as mighty nowe as he was in thoſe dayes and is now as able to flea boeth you and youres in one night,<note place="margin">Exodi. xiiii.</note> as he was to flea al the firſte borne of the Egiptyans: And then who ſhal haue the ſpoile? Be warned betime, leaſt ye repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te to late leaue of your gredie deſire to pul away the liueynge from the cleargy, and ſeke dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentlye to ſet ſuche miniſters in the churche as be able and wyl enſtruct the people in al pointes of theyr dutie, that you with them and they with you may eſcape the wrath of God that hangeth preſently ouer you both. <note place="margin">Ionas. iii.</note>The kinge &amp; Citizens of Neniue were not aſhamed to fitte in ſackecloth and in aſhes lamentynge their ſynnes and there vpon
<pb facs="tcp:5414:16"/> founde mercye. Wherefore if ye wyll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ynde mercye, ye muſte not be aſhamed to do the lyke, for certenlye the greatnes of your ſinnes importeth as preſent diſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to you as if ye were the ſame Niniuites y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ionas was ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto. Be not aſhamed ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore to proclame a ſolemne faſt thorowe out the whole realme, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all at once w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one voyce we may crye vnto god for mercy. Leaue of your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munions in a corner, &amp; come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> temples y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men may ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye regard y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords inſtitucion. Breake your bread to the pore, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al men may ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye regard faſtyng. For y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is the true faſt, to refraine the meate &amp; drinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> accuſtomably we were wout to take &amp; geue the ſame (or the value therof) to the nedy. So ſhal you both fele &amp; know theyr diſeaſe, and eaſe it alſo. Truſt not to your great nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of valiant warriours, neither to your mightye prouiſions, but reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber what befel to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lofernes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtout captaine of king Nobucho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ddnozer, when he woulde not harken to the right aduice of Achior hys vndercaptaine.</p>
            <p>For certenly I ſay vnto you,<note place="margin">Iudeth. v.</note> god was neuer more redy to deliuer his people of Iſrael fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oppreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at al times when they walkinge in his wayes committed their cauſe vnto him: then he is now redy to deliuer al chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that do wyth lyke confidence cal vpon him,
<pb facs="tcp:5414:17"/> If you therfore wyl not he arken vnto Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or his counſel, but determine to torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t him when ye ſhal triumpth ouer the reſt: doubte you not but Iudith ſhal cut of al your hedes on after another &amp; god ſhal ſtrike youre re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinew w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch a feare,<note place="margin">Iudeth. xiii. and .xv.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> none ſhalbe ſo bolde as once to tourne hys face. Yea if there were no men left on liue to put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in feare, they ſhould be feared wyth ſhadowes. And though ther were no gonnes to ſhote at the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet the ſtones of the ſtrete ſhuld not ceaſe to flye emonge them, by the mightye power of God, who wyl rather make of euery graſſe in the field a man, then ſuch as truſt in hym ſhould be ouerrun or kept in oppreſſion. Be warned therfore, &amp; ſeke not to kepe the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mones of England in ſlauery. For that is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> next way to deſtroie your ſelues. For if thei co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit theyr cauſe to God &amp; quiet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues in their vocacion, beyng contented with op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, if goddes wyll be ſo: then ſhal ye be ſure that God wyll fyghte for them, and ſo are ye ouer matched. But if they wyl nedes take in hand to reuenge theyr owne wronge God wyll fyght agaynſt you boeth, ſo that you boeth conſumynge one the other ſhall ſhortly be made a praye to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ye doubt leaſt of al the world.</p>
            <p>As you tender your owne wealth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:5414:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> and the publique wealth of thys noble realme of Englande, which God hath enri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched wyth ſo manye and ſo greate commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, &amp; as you deſyre to vſe and enioye the ſame, and not to be led away captiue into a ſtraynge nacion, or elſe be cruelly murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red among your wyues, kinſfolke and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and finallye to be damned for euer: ſo loke vpon theſe cauſes of Sedicion, and do your beſt endeuour to put them awaie. You that be oppreſſed, I ſay, refer youre cauſe to God. And you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue oppreſſed, lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t your ſo doinge and do the office of your callinge, in defendinge the innocente and fedinge the nedye. Let not couetyſe conſtraine you to robbe the people of that porcion which they paie to haue godly miniſters to enſtruct the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their duetie, and to releue the vnweldy that be not able to labour for theire fode Be carefull and diligent to ſeke for ſuche mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and when you haue founde them let them haue al that the people paye yearely out of their encreaſe, that they may liue ther on and miniſter vnto the pore, out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame.</p>
            <p>Thus doinge, ye ſhall not onelye eſcape the vengeance that hangeth preſentlye ouer you but alſo be rewarded at goddes hande boeth with excedinge plenti of al good thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges in this life, &amp; alſo with life euerlaſtinge
<pb facs="tcp:5414:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> when nature ſhal ende the ſame. Where as if ye wyl not take counſell but remayne ſtyl in your wycked purpoſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Pharao nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>domites were neuer ſo hardened as you ſhalbe, neyther is the remembraunce of theyr diſtruccion ſo terible to vs, as the diſtruccion of you ſhalbe to others that ſhall come af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The ſpirite of GOD worcke in youre her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that ye beynge admoniſhed of the ſword that is commynge, maye by repentaunce of your ſyn eſcape the daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger therof. </p>
            <closer>☞ So be it ☜</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:5414:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
